# 这就跟狮子脑子似的
It’s like a lion brain
# 你看见没有 大粒 这叫狮子头
Look at how big they are. This is “Shizitou” (aka "Lion Head")
# 清炖狮子头
“Shizitou” stew
# 今天我们又回到我们原来
Today we’re back to our very first
# 四弟的小屋了 特别高兴
Si Di’s room. Very happy.
# 四边摄一摄 还是原来的样子是吧
Look around. Still the same as the very beginning
# 您是不是感到非常亲切 就特别亲切
Don’t you feel very warm and familiar. Very warm and familiar
# 以前做过是红烧的
We have made braised “Shizitou” before
# 这次咱们做一个国宴常规用的
Today we are going to make one used to serve state banquets
# 清炖狮子头
Stewed “Shizitou”
# 清炖狮子头因为是常规的国宴用的
Because this is for state banquets
# 它清淡 过去咱们叫葵花斩肉
Its taste is mild. We used to call it “Kui Hua Zhan Rou”
# 我们先把肉先切成片
First of all, we cut the meat into slices
# 您是用什么粉子  用玉米淀粉就行
What kind of starch you are using? Corn starch is fine
# 切要切成肉丝
Cut it into strips
# 然后切成石榴籽大的丁儿
And dice them into pomegranate seed size
# 现在好多人切都小是吧 对
A lot of people cut them too small right? Yes
# 清炖狮子头有很多方法
There are lots of methods cooking “Shizitou”
# 比如按照应季的
For example, seasonally
# 里边可以放马蹄 春天可以放春笋
You can put water chestnuts. You can put spring bamboo shoots in spring
# 秋天可以放大闸蟹的蟹黄 蟹黄狮子头
Put Chinese mitten crab roe and make “crab roe shizitou”
# 到冬天可以晾点风鸡 风鸡狮子头
You can make “feng ji” (dried chicken) in winter and make “feng ji Shizitou”
# 这个狮子头炖出来以后
After it is fully cooked
# 汤清肉烂 口味清淡
Soup will be clear, and meat will be pulpy. Taste will be mild.
# 你看这狮子头经过炖制以后
After being stewed
# 它油脂它就出去了
The oil inside can come out
# 有句话要特别要说清楚的
Want to make it clear enough
# 叫细切粗剁
It’s called “Cu Qie Xi Duo” (cut carefully and chop roughly)
# 它上面肉呈颗粒状
The meat is granular
# 剁完之后这肉你看 上劲儿了
After gets chopped, the meat “shang jing”
# 它黏度起来了 好了
It starts to become sticky
# 然后能粘连在一起 行了好了
Thus, it can stick together. Alright
# 你看到没有 有粘性 肥瘦相融
Look at it. Sticky. Fat and lean part of meat mixed up.
# 下边咱进行第二项 马蹄拍一下
Now we are going to do the second step. Smash the water chestnuts
# 马蹄放狮子头里边
Put water chestnuts
# 它有一个反差口感 另外还解油腻
To create an opposite taste and balance the oily taste
# 拍完了还不能斩太细
Do not chop it too small
# 葱姜酒水
Water infused with scallions, ginger and wine
# 黄酒 花雕
Huang jiu (rice wine), Hua diao (rice wine)
# 下一步我们先把锅点着了
Next step, let’s turn on the burner
# 放水不放水 放好了
Do we add water? Water was already poured in
# 这锅里头放这葱姜也得有个数量
There has to be exact numbers of scallions and ginger
# 三块葱三片姜
Three chunks of scallions and three slices of ginger
# 到时候往出挑的时候
The time you pick them out
# 我要拣出 得有三块四块 你心里有数
You have to remember how many you have to pick up
# 咱开始和馅儿了啊
We’re going to make filling
# 肉是六百克 一斤二两肉
The meat is 600 grams, One jin and two liang (0.6 kg)
# 现在有将近四百克（葱姜酒水）水
Now we have about 400 g water (scallion, ginger, wine made water)
# 但是这水不能全搁进去 就先搁一部分
Don’t pour water all in. Just pour a portion of water at first
# 淀粉两勺 大约在三十克
Two spoons of starch, about 30g
# 胡椒 白胡椒
Pepper. White pepper
# 少许
A little bit
# 盐 十克 清炖狮子头盐多一点不要紧
Salt. 10g. It doesn’t matter to have more salt to make stewed “Shizitou”
# 因为它在炖制当中会分解到这水里头
Because salt will dissolve in water during stewing
# 有的时候网友会看这盐是不是搁多了
Some people may ask whether the salt is too much
# 它不是搁多了 多不了
No, it’s not. It can't be
# 顺着方向 朝着一个方向
Follow the same direction
# 搅动 摔打
Stir and beat
# 这个盐不够 它摔打上劲儿不太容易
It’s hard to make meat “shang jing” if salt is not enough
# 盐的渗透力非常强
Salt has strong osmosis
# 另外还有刚才忘了跟网友交代一下
Besides,  I forgot to mention that
# 肉的肥瘦比例很重要
The ratio of fat to lean is important
# 肥四瘦六
40% fat and 60% lean
# 有人说了我不爱吃那么多肥肉
Some people are saying I don’t like fat
# 但是也要达到肥三瘦七
At least 30% fat and 70% lean
# 肥的占三成 瘦的占七成
Fat is 30% and lean is 70%
# 脂肪过于少 吃的口感不行
It won’t taste good with less fat
# 它没有弹性
It won’t be springy
# 你看这水没了 我们再加水
No water. We add more water
# 再搁点盐 二次下盐
More salt. It’s the second time we add salt.
# 为什么啊 手感 弹性不够
Why? Because it doesn’t feel elastic
# 说明这盐不够 淀粉可还差一点
Which means salt is not enough.  Starch is also not enough.
# 这就是您的（经验）
This is based on your experience
# 没有什么 我有绝对把握
I will never be absolutely confident
# 说一下弄得就合适 要有二次的
To make it perfect at the first time. There has to be a second time
# 你看这黏度不够 黏度不够您还打水
It’s not sticky enough. You add more water even it is not sticky?
# 那也得打水 到时候吃的时候不够嫩
There has to be some water or it’s not tender enough
# 你看一点点的
A little bit
# 这水千万别一次性加足 慢慢打慢慢渗
Don’t add too much water at one time. Add water slowly.
# 大爷您摔的还挺厉害
Da Ye you beat it hard
# 不摔厉害不行 它不起劲儿
It won’t “qi jing” if you don’t beat it hard
# 你这锅也开了 马上就炖上了
Water is boiling. Ready to go.
# 马蹄 打上劲儿以后放马蹄
Water chestnuts. Add water chestnuts once the meat “shang jing”
# 大爷这马蹄还不少呢 大约一百五十克
Da Ye, there are lots of water chestnuts. About 150g.
# 摔馅的碗底一定要大
The bowl used to beat the filling has to be large
# 它摔的时候piapia
You can hear the sound of “Pia Pia” as you beat it
# 家伙事儿小了
The bowl is small
# 这底儿小 家伙事儿可不小
The bottom is small, but the bowl is not small
# 太大了也不行 好家伙 它就占了二斤肉
Too large is not good as well. It weighs like two jin (1 kg) meat
# 我们现在弄一个水淀粉的碗
Now we are going to make a bowl of slurry
# 然后大爷那小手就抖起来
Da Ye, show us your shaking hands
# 我本来就抖
My hands always shake
# 锅开了
The water is boiling
# 咱们按标准做大约在二两吧
We make standard sized meatballs, about 2 liang (100g) each
# 您这个太大了 吃不了
This is too big. Too much for one
# 俩人一个 不是一人吃
One for two persons not for one person
# 一个人吃你肯定吃不完
One person can’t finish it
# 如果有蟹黄 现在可以把蟹黄放进去
If you are using crab roe, you can put it now
# 蟹肉放到这个馅里头 蟹黄放到浮头
Mix the crab meat with meat filling and put crab roe on the surface
# 我放着海米行不行 海米不行
Can I add “Hai mi” (dried shrimp)? “Hai mi” is not ok
# 为什么不行 行是行 但是要切碎
Why not? You can but you have to mince it
# 您这狮子头个儿可不小 得二两
Your “Shizitou” is not small. There is 2 liang (100g).
# 淀粉使得表面光滑
Starch makes surface smooth
# 加强肉表面的拉力
Strengthen the surface tension
# 遇热它糊化表面特别光滑
Starch gelatinizes once heated, which makes meatball surface smooth.
# 还是徒弟会说 遇热糊化
Disciple is smart: starch gelatinizes once heated
# 慢慢炖着去吧
Stew it slowly
# 为什么要放五个
Why you put five
# 它互相挤着点它不跑
The meatballs won’t move if they are squeezed by each other
# 如果你放四个它在里边跟游泳似的
It’s like swimming in the soup if you only put four in
# 在里边它不会来回跑是吧
So they won’t move, right?
# 这里面要放点什么呢 黄酒
What are we going to add? Huang Jiu (rice wine)
# 你没放多少 不要多
You didn’t add a lot. Not too much.
# 因为那馅儿里边有了
Because we’ve already added some in the filling
# 放点胡椒
Add some pepper
# 还发点味精么 这都不放了
Some MSG? no we don’t
# 等最后再调味
We don't season until the end
# 我们讲的就是
What we are saying is
# 烹调前 烹调中 烹调后
Before cooking, during cooking and after cooking
# 三个调味的环节
There are three stages for seasoning
# 三种全要加味儿
Season at each of the three stages
# 要掌握准确
Have to be precise
# 有沫要把它打干净
Skim off the scum completely
# 我们这个狮子头现在OK了
Now the “Shizitou” is good right now
# 我再说一个
Another one
# 这个直接烧 这也叫炖
This is called “Shao” which is also called “Dun” (stew)
# 这叫什么 这叫不隔水炖
This is called stewing in water
# 有的叫隔水炖
There is another method called stewing above water
# 隔水炖就是把它放在蒸锅里边
Stewing above water is to put it in the steamer
# 因为它隔着水了 隔水蒸
Because it is separated from water and steamed.
# 这两种方法它有一个什么样的好处
What are the benefits of these two methods?
# 不隔水炖 它出来的汤比较浓香味厚
Stewing in water makes soup taste rich and smell good
# 但是汤容易发白发浑
But soup looks white and cloudy
# 要蒸的话 汤清 肉嫩
Steaming makes soup clean and meat tender
# 但是有时候油漂出来的少
But oil come out less
# 这样直接炖的它油出来得多
Stewing in water makes more oil come out
# 你看为什么说
This is why we say that
# 做酒店做高档宴席的时候
When restaurants cook for high-end banquets
# 这汤炖完了就不要了 换成清鸡汤
The soup is thrown away and substituted by clear chicken broth
# 夏天那时候就爽了
So good in summer
# 小火
Simmer
# 狮子头现在上火炖 要炖多长时间
We are going to simmer “Shizitou”. How long will it take
# 两个小时甚至到两个半小时
Two hours or even up to two and a half hours
# 到三个小时都可以
Or even three hours?
# 别太长了
Don’t be too long
# 其实两个半小时是最好的
Actually, two and a half hours is the best
# 炖出来了以后肉酥软烂 汤清味浓
That way the meat is pulpy, soup is fresh and taste is strong
# 掀锅了啊二伯 大爷我看您休息够了
Er Bai, I’m going to open the lid. Da Ye you must have had a good rest
# 开锅滚滚
Water is boiling
# 我们刚才说的 三截葱 一截
Like we just said. Three chunks of scallions
# 大爷这白菜没盖上啊
Da Ye, where is the napa cabbage
# 白菜咱就不搁了 这个季节白菜不好
We don’t add napa cabbage this time. Napa cabbage is not good this season
# 这还一片葱 这又一片
There is a slice of scallion. Another one.
# 您刚才这做法都是很传统的
Your cooking method is very traditional
# 这就跟狮子脑子似的
It looks like lion brain
# 你见没有 大粒 这叫狮子头
Look at how big they are. This is called “Shizitou”
# 你兄弟不是干淮扬菜的
I am not a professional on Huaiyang Cuisine
# 但是能说出来吧
But I can tell
# 您这是大师啊
You are master
# 大师两回事儿 大师多了
it has nothing to do with master. Too many masters.
# 我们这时候要尝尝汤
Now we are going to have a taste of soup
# 因为我就加了点胡椒 黄酒
Because I just added pepper and huang jiu (rice wine)
# 盐没加
I didn’t add salt
# 盐在狮子头里边 看它渗透有多少
Salt is inside the “Shizitou”. Let’s see how much it dissolved
# 正合适
Perfect
# 说一句什么话 说句心里话
To be honest
# 现在就合适
Right now is perfect
# 但是为了让它更加丰满一点
But I want to make it richer
# 我知道您为什么 再加点盐
I know why. Add more salt
# 因为你还得加上油菜呢
Because you are adding baby bok choy
# 狮子头好了 我们这边又取了一个锅
“Shizitou” is ready. We got another pot.
# 这油菜必须要焯一下
The baby bok choy has to be blanched
# 因为它有青气味和涩味
Because it has raw and bitter taste
# 南方的油菜心叫矮脚黄
The southern baby bok choy is called “Ai Jiao Huang”
# 就那种大脑袋的
The one with big stem
# 那个菜心好 它甜 而且还面
That baby boy choy is good. Sweet and pulpy
# 咱北方的菜心就差点
The northern baby bok choy is not as good
# 所以要事先给它烫一下
So we blanch it at first
# 一方水土养一方人
The unique features of a local environment always give special characteristics to its inhabitants
# 北方的油菜就稍微有点涩苦
The northern baby bok choy is a little bit bitter
# 但是一焯就没味儿了
But its bitterness disappears once it is blanched
# 焯油菜的别超太嫩了
Don’t make baby bok choy too tender
# 因为它变色以后在锅里面略微的
After the color changes
# 略微的给它再炖一会
Stew it for a short time
# 头朝外也行 头朝里也行
You can put the stem either inward or outward
# 现在这个砂锅我给稍微开一下火
Now I am going to turn up the flame.
# 让开的大一点 彻底开了
Turn higher. Make it fully cooked
# 这圆砂锅就可以上桌了
The round pot is ready to serve
# 这就成型了
This is what it is.
# 隋坡 好了啊
Sui Po, we are all good.
# 圆砂锅上桌 垫着一个盘子
Put the round pot on table with a plate at the bottom
# 这上去你看客人要见到
When guests look at it
# 这个狮子头 能不爱吃吗
No wonder guests love it
# 一掀锅哗哗就开着
Water is boiling when opening the lid
# 咱们来一个开锅仪式
Let’s have a pot-opening ceremony
# 一掀锅
Open the pot
# 闻闻 有一种清香味 热气腾腾
Smell it. There is a fresh fragrance. Hot.
# 过去那年代人都实在 这东西都大
People in the past were honest. Everything was big.
# 二伯 吃这狮子头应该是要拿勺吃
Er Bai, you have to eat “Shizitou” with spoon
# 你要拿那筷子吃
with chopsticks
# 如果说能夹起来的话
If you can pick it up
# 这狮子头就（失败）了
The “Shizitou” fails
# 所以必须用勺
You have to use spoon
# 二伯你看我给您表演一个
Er Bai, let me show you
# 你看一扫
Look, brush
# 大爷先吃 二伯必须先吃
Da Ye you go first. Er Bai has to be the first.
# 隋坡你看它抖 你看它颤
Sui Po, look at it. It’s shaking.
# 这不是我手颤
It’s not my hand shaking
# 隋坡 这是你的 谢谢师父
Sui Po this is yours. Thanks, master
# 隋坡这做绝了
Sui Po, this is fantastic
# 好吃吧 好吃
Tasty? tasty
# 给师父尝一个
Let my master have a taste
# 我尝一口  自我欣赏
Let me have a taste. Self-esteem.
# 这咸味拿的太准了
The salty taste is perfect
# 一辈子宝贵经验在这放着
With lifelong precious experience
# 入口即化
It melts once you put it in your mouth
# 你看这么多肉它不腻
It’s not oily even with lots of meat
# 吃完了那种又清香 又不腻
It tastes fresh and not oily
# 多拿几个勺
Get more spoons
# 让我们外边小饭骨尝尝
Let our “Xiao Fan Gu” have a try